Finding aid to the Ivan T. Gorokhoff papers CA.MS.00151
Smith College Archives
Ivan T. Gorokhoff Family papers
1902-1991
Smith College Archives
Gorokhoff, Ivan T., 1879-1949
CA.MS.00151
3.458 linear feet (6 containers)
Ivan Timofeevich Gorokhoff was born in Leschinskaya, Russia on November 14, 1879. He was music director at Smith College from 1918-1945. The collection contains documents related to family matters and Gorokhoff's musical career.
Biographical / Historical
Ivan Timofeevich Gorokhoff was born in Leschinskaya, Russia on November 14, 1879. He was educated at a seminary in Kursk with the prospect of becoming a Russian Orthodox priest, but instead focused on choral conducting. He was Choirmaster at the Theological Seminary, Kursk (1904), of the Kursk Cathedral Choir (1904-1906) and at the Synod Choirmaster School (1906-1912) before coming to the United States in 1912. Upon arrival in New York he became the Choirmaster of the Russian Cathedral (1912-1918) and came to Smith College in 1918. At Smith College he conducted various choral groups until his retirement in 1945. Gorokhoff died in New Haven, Connecticut on January 24, 1949.
Ivan T. Gorokhoff was married to Raisa Alexandrovna (September 3, 1895-June 29, 1973) in Moscow, Russia in 1914.
Galina Ivanovna Gorokhoff, the daughter of Ivan and Raisa Gorokhoff, was born March 7, 1921 in Northampton, Massachusetts. She was a graduate of the Northampton School for Girls (1939) and Smith College (Class of 1943). From 1964 to 1979 she held positions at Yale University in the Library and Art Gallery. From 1979 to 1983 she was a research associate at the Department of Paintings, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston and from 1983-1984 was a researcher at the Childs Gallery, Boston. Later she was an editor at the Archaeological Institute of America. She died in Waltham, Massachusetts on July 7, 1991. Ms. Gorokhoff wrote and co-authored articles and books on numerous American artists and curated numerous exhibitions of American artists for American galleries and museums.
Arrangement
The Gorokhoff papers are divided into three series:
Series I.: Ivan T. Gorokhoff papers (1902 -1949) contain documents related to his life in Russia, a scrapbook of his career (1913-1932) in the United States, letters of appreciation to him upon his retirement from Smith College in 1945, correspondence from Sergi Rachmaninoff (1942), portraits and photographs, memorabilia and recordings of chorus he conducted.
Series II: Raisa Gorokhoff papers contain legal documents (1952-1973).
Series III: Galina Ivanovna Gorokhoff papers contain legal documents, curriculum vitae and memorabilia.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Ivan T. Gorokhoff Family papers were created by Ivan T. Gorokhoff and Galina Ivanovna Gorokhoff and donated to the College Archives.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, legal documents, scrapbooks, recordings, photographs, curriculum vitae and memorabilia.
- Series I - Ivan T. Gorokhoff
  - Russian language documents including school certificates, 1914-1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Naturalization and death certificates, 1925-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 19 -19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical materials including a typescript of a biographical sketch of Ivan and Raisa, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Ivan, Raisa and family members, 19uu-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Legal documents on the settlement of the estate of Ivan, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Score with notations by Ivan of Missa O quam gloriosium, by Tomas Luis de Victoria, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Concert program for concert of the Russian Cathedral Choir at Springfield, Mass., Mar. 3, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Yearbook (1946) of the Northampton School for Girls dedicated to Gorokhoff (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Sergi Rachmaninoff, program of a concert conducted by Gorokhoff and newspaper clippings, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Holograph letters of appreciation, typescripts of materials gathered by Smith College and documents from Gorokhoff's retirement, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 11-32)
  - Scrapbook of newspapers clippings, letters and memorabilia from Gorokhoff's career in the United States, 1913-1932 (Box 2)
  - Yearbook from a Russian educational institution, 1902-1903 (Box 4)
  - Recordings of works conducted by Gorokhoff: 1. Smith College Glee Club and Princeton University Chapel Choir in Byrd, Ave verum; Gibbons, Hosanna to the Son; Victoria, Missa O quam gloriosium; 2. Smith College Glee Club and Amherst Chapel Choir in Great vesper service, based on traditional melodies of the Russian Church by Sergei Rachmaninoff., 1940s (Box 4)
  - Choral Concert - Great Vesper Service, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, clippings, letters (Box 5)
  - Photograph albums (2) (Box 6)
- Series II - Raisa Gorokhoff
  - Naturalization certificate, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Will and probate documents, 1959-1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Cemetery documents, 1949? (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series III - Galina Ivanovna Gorokhoff
  - Curriculum vitae, 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - High school and college items, 1939-1943 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings and memorabilia, 1943-1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Birth, marriage and death certificates, 1921-1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Divorce documents, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Wills and probate documents, 1967-1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Passports, etc., 1976-1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Galina Ivanovna Gorokhoff, 1974-1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Poster for a lecture by Erik Trinkaus (Galina's son) at the College de France, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)